<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jekyll on companionway</title>
    <link>/tags/jekyll/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Jekyll on companionway</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved - companionway - 2016</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 10:57:45 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/jekyll/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Switched to Hugo</title>
      <link>/post/post-title/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 10:57:45 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/post-title/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am swtiching from jekyll to hugo for flat file for a Content Managment System (CMS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It comes as a binary file that runs on pretty much any platform. A single file&amp;hellip; without a list of dependencies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could stop with the last reason and it would be enough&amp;hellip; but I have to say that the file tree used in hugo is simple, and simple is beautiful. As Einstein once said:
&amp;gt;“Make things as simple as possible, but not simpler.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is written in googles go language&amp;hellip; so it is fast and portable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is closely tied to git so it can easily be used on github and for version maintence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it builds a clean directory [./public/] for the full site deploy and this can be rsync&amp;rsquo;d to where ever you like.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;No frustrating&lt;/em&gt; version incompatiblities (or at least very minimal) - unlike jekyll which seemed to break on me every few months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hugo is relatively mature and has a huge developer backing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;configurable and changed without challenges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lots of themes to choose from&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as the Hugo websites states - it makes the web fun again&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did I mention that it is a single executable file?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reference:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/#intro&#34;&gt;gohugo.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy
-g-&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>startbootstrap-clean theme contact form</title>
      <link>/post/2015-04-03-post1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-04-03-post1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Getting the contact form to work on godaddy hosting was a trip, an ugly
trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contact form built into the jekyll startbootstrap-clean theme coding
is a bit convoluted and needed tweaking to get it working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;first you change the mail/contact_me.php to include to your email address
(no problem there)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;but it failed so I used google chrome developer tool (Ctrl-Shft-I) to diagnose what was failing.
It was looking for the php script at /contact/mail/contact_me.php instead of /mail/contact_me.php
(easily fixed by moving it).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;by the way - this form does not pass the POST variables directly to the on script - it uses js/bootstrap-clean.js
(which has been minified into js/bootstrap-clean-min.js) to validate the form entries and passes it on to contact_me.php
as POST variables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;however, on godaddy hosting they restrict things quite a bit and you need to use their tools
to send email. They place into your basic web site gdform.php and webformmailer.php (which is a link). I tried
replacing contact_me.php with each of these&amp;hellip; only gdform.php worked. Their gdform.php script actually writes
out your POSTED variables into a dated file (eg gform_8935621) into you $HOME/data/ directory. A cron job periodically
mails out any gform_xxxxxxx file it finds to you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bottom line &amp;hellip; I saved the original contact_me.php off and then on my godaddy site I copied gdform.php to /contact/mail/contact_me.php
and all problems solved. Your contact email will eventually come when the cron runs to send it. You can check new conntact requests
by looking for $HOME/data/gdform-xxxxxxx files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure if you sync files form you local machine to your website that you change
your local contact_me.php similarly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy
-g-&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This web site..</title>
      <link>/post/2015-04-01-post2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-04-01-post2/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;this-website:4224afbb7574788ef8279bacbff78e41&#34;&gt;This website&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; was created (and is maintained) using jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But getting here was a bit of a struggle.&lt;br /&gt;
I started using Jekyll quite some time ago. I love ruby and when I&lt;br /&gt;
found Jekyll I thought my mutual love for ruby and website design
had perfectly come together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not so fast there buckeroo. I could not easily manage themes in a way&lt;br /&gt;
that satisfied me&amp;hellip; so I went exploring. I tried dozens of flat CMS&lt;br /&gt;
generators. My journey lasted months. I was very impressed with gravCMS&lt;br /&gt;
but I still fought with theme manipulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sinatra and nanco were inspiring but somewhere I came across a blog&lt;br /&gt;
which I don&amp;rsquo;t recall now, that had me building my own theme. That&lt;br /&gt;
gave me enought traction to begin to understand how to control themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What brought me back to jekyll was github. I have been building out&lt;br /&gt;
my github site and it is built with jekyll. It is hard to fight success&lt;br /&gt;
and obviously jekyll has had a strong history of success with github. Then&lt;br /&gt;
I pounded a handful of themes available and recently found myself working&lt;br /&gt;
more and more with the startbootstrap-clean-blog-jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More to come&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>