<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on companionway</title>
    <link>/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on companionway</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved - companionway - 2016</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 14:27:35 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Raspberry Pi MagicMirror on a Touchscreen with Alexa and fauxmo</title>
      <link>/post/post-title/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 14:27:35 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/post-title/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;warning-what-follows-is-a-cascade-of-issues-and-lessons-learned-but-just-plain-fun&#34;&gt;Warning: what follows is a cascade of issues and lessons learned&amp;hellip; but just plain fun!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-goal&#34;&gt;The goal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is designed to provide a reliable MagicMirror2 on a Raspberry Pi fitted with a 5 inch touchscreen that doubles to provide browsing if needed. This comes from a desire to have a quick aide in the kitchen that reports standard information when needed or a browser for looking up and displaying recipes etc.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is a raspberry pi with one wire that stands on its edge without a case and has a 5 inch display. The display can show any of the modules provided for magicmirror2 on command to Alexa or stop magicmirror on command. The rasbian desktop along with an inboard keyboard pad and touch &amp;ldquo;pen&amp;rdquo; allows you to launch a browser (or any other program) and navigate to any url. When the desktop is idle a screensaver comes up with anynumber of pleasing animations - selectable and can be rotated with screen blanking possible as well. The backlight of the screen is enough to act as a soothing nightlight. All in all, I am very pleased (and so is my wife) with the final result of this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a LOT of information here and lots of steps but it is worth it and you will definately learn lots of useful tricks. I am sure there are many improvements that could be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/k-pi1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;Kitchen Pi Image:1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;materials&#34;&gt;Materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hardware
- rasberry pi (in my case a model 3) with powersuppy
- 5 inch touchscreen with plastic pen
- USB storage (optional but recommended)
- you will need a temporary keyboard/mouse attached to set things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software
- berryboot (which will load rasbian)
- apache2 and php
- magicmirror2 and various modules
- fauxmo (from Maker Musings)
- software for the touchscreen including touch a calibration tool
- matchbox-keyboard
- xcreensaver&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;problems-encountered&#34;&gt;Problems Encountered&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were lots of challenges that thwarted what seemed like a simple goal to achieve.
- fauxmo needs a little more documentation on how to build the &amp;ldquo;virtual switch&amp;rdquo; html code. I will proyvide a sample here.
- Alexa tends to not forget discovered devices when told to find devices again.
- Troubleshooting the HEADER return code from html and php scripts is essential to making all the players between Alexa/fauxmo/and the &amp;ldquo;virtual switch&amp;rdquo; happy.
- a 5 inch touchscreen is too small for a default MagicMirror run but there are solutions.
- turning the display and getting the touchscreen calibrated correctly can be difficult until you know how to do it
- the software that comes with the touchscreen will clobber a berryboot config - and pretty much any other custom config you have for the raspberry pi.
- finding ways to get the html/web server to execute commands within a users X display can be daunting
Y- when php executes and external shell command - things can silently hang with out easy indication.
- magicmirror2 can be a little overwhelming with npm and electron running under it - especially when you are trying to get the webserver (and ultimately Alexa/Amazon echo) to control it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;shoutouts&#34;&gt;Shoutouts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;berryboot works well and provides (at least for me) a more reliable raspberry pi OS file system solution than an SD card only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;magicmirror2 is just plain fun&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fauxmo (a wemo emulator) is a crazy easy solution to using Alexa to turn on or off anything if you are willing to do a little coding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;php remains my goto language for simple web projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the touchscreens for the raspberry pi have come a long way in that they basically plug onto the raspberry pi board, do a little software tweaking and it is up and ready to go.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;xscreensaver - I gained a renewed respect for this fun application&amp;hellip; it continues to provide fun idle entertainment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;solving-the-problems&#34;&gt;Solving the problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;berryboot-on-a-raspberry-pi&#34;&gt;Berryboot on a Raspberry Pi&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just do it. Too many times I have had SD cards loose their minds. The filesystem burps with all the activity and you are forced
to reboot the raspberry pi; hopefully the filesystem repair goes smoothly on reboot. I am inherently lazy so getting up and rebooting the raspberry pi is not my first choice, especially when you have them hidden away in some back compartment. Berryboot
allows you to boot from a USB storage device like a USB stick or a USD drive. You can also have it boot across the network from
another storage device but I will leave that up to you. In my case I use a (cheap) 16G USB stick and all my raspberry pi servers have wifi.
Berryboot allows you to store multiple OS distros and select which to boot. You can save and restore images and download new OS distros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;go download the latest berryboot zip to your PC/laptop &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.berryterminal.com/doku.php/berryboot&#34;&gt;berryboot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;assuming your SD card has a standard (FAT) partition just copy all the zip contents to it. You can quicly format
your SD card with one partition using your camera. You may want to remove any directories that your camera might create first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put the Berryboot SD card in the raspberry pi making sure your display, USB storage and wifi are attached and boot up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your display is an HDMI TV you can use your remote control to navigate but I find that cumbersome so I added a USB keyboard/touchpad like the Rii mini X1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First get the wifi connected &amp;hellip; near the bottom of the Berryboot screen is abutton for that. Configure the SSID and password and then you can tell Berryboot to download any of its prepared OS distros. One challenge is that Berryboot needs an OS that has been constructed for its use but down&amp;rsquo;t let this hold you back. A list of images can be found here: &lt;a href=&#34;http://berryboot.alexgoldcheidt.com/images/&#34;&gt;berryboot images&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After it boots go look at /boot/config.txt to see how the magick works. Keep in mind that if this file gets clobberred berryboot will be toast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enjoy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;magicmirror2-on-the-raspberry-pi&#34;&gt;MagicMirror2 on the raspberry pi&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can &amp;ldquo;seem&amp;rdquo; more difficult than it really is. I do pretty much everything by ssh at the commandline.
- ssh into the raspberry pi
- You can use the git source for MagicMirror2 but really this next command saves steps and is the first recommendation in the docs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;curl -sL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/MichMich/MagicMirror/master/installers/raspberry.sh | bash
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of needed dependencies will get loaded - additionally you may have to use apt install node-legacy (with sudo of course).
This will build out MagicMirror off your $HOME directory. I didn&amp;rsquo;t like this a first but it simply works so best not to fight it.
- cd ~/MagicMirror
- run
DISPLAY=:0
npm start &amp;amp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Now use your browser and go hit http://[raspberry-pi-IP]:8080.
This can run without a web server or along side a web server as long as the browser (or any other application) isn&#39;t using the 8080 port.

![alt text](/img/k-pi2.jpg &amp;quot;Kitchen Pi Image:2&amp;quot;)

MagicMirror can look a little intimidating but have no fear. It uses lots of javascript (.js files) but it wraps those files with electron to create a &amp;quot;running HTML/js/node.js/CSS application&amp;quot; on the local machine. Read more on electron here: [electron.atom.io](http://electron.atom.io/) and then it uses npm (node package manager) to assemble all the java script and install all the dependencies. More info on npm can be found here: [npmjs](https://www.npmjs.com/)

Now we have MagicMirror running. Lets turn our attention using the display on the raspberry pi.

There are lots of changes you can make to MagicMirror but lets move on and we will explore those changes after we reconfigure the touch screen to a portrait display instead of the default landscape mode.

## X display on Raspberry Pi
Configure the raspberry pi to boot up with X windows running.
- log in to the raspberry pi with ssh (by the way - to log in an redirect any X apps to your local display use `ssh -X user@raspberry-IP`) 
- run `sudo raspi-config` and set the boot up to GUI (Graphical User Interface) appropriately.

Now it gets a little tricky here. You can configure the server to boot right into the GUI and bring up MagicMirror as the `pi` user (which is the default) but I changed this up a little. 
The rasberry pi default setup for rasbian (jessie) will set the user &#39;pi&#39; as the default X login so I wanted to change that to my own username - here is how to do it. Edit as the superuser (use sudo) the `/etc/lightdm/lightdm,conf` file and change this line appropriately:
```autologin-user=yourname```
There, moved one more step forward.

## xscreensaver

Add xscreensaver to both your desktop/laptop and the raspberry pi.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;sudo pt install xscreensaver xscreensaver-data xscreensaver-data-extra  xscreensaver-gl&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;I added xscreensaver for several reasons. It provides a console to control how long the screen will stay active until it blanks and
the screensaver screens provide interesting displays on an idle screen. I set up what I wanted on my laptop and then transferred
the $HOME/.xscreensaver file to the home dir of the raspberry pi. 

You have to run xscreenserver-demo on the magicmirror server to get it to configure properly on that server.

## configure the 5 inch touchscreen

For this project I needed a keyboard/mouse-pad for two phases, installing berryboot and for configuring the touchscreen.
For my touchscreen (yours may be different) I needed these files
 - 5.0 Inch display User Guide.pdf
 - LCD-show-161112.tar.gz
 - Xinput-calibrator_0.7.5-1_armhf.zip
Go to this website for info: [5inch HDMI LCD](http://www.waveshare.com/wiki/5inch_HDMI_LCD)

BE CAREFULL HERE... if your follow the instructions and run their install script (not necessary) you will overwrite
the /boot/config.txt file and clobber the berryboot you installed above. Took me a bit to figure that one out. You only
need to add a few lines to the /boot/config.txt - which is essentially what their install script does.
Just add these lines to /boot/config.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#####
hdmi_group=2
hdmi_mode=1
hdmi_mode=87
hdmi_cvt 800 480 60 6 0 0 0
dtoverlay=ads7846,cs=1,penirq=25,penirq_pull=2,speed=50000,keep_vref_on=0,swapxy=0,pmax=255,xohms=150,xmin=200,xmax=3900,ymin=200,ymax=3900
#display_rotate=1
#display_rotate=2
display_rotate=3
avoid_warnings=1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;disable_overscan=1
start_x=1
###&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;I loaded these before the berryboot settings and it worked fine. You may want to experiment with the rotation to find what works
best for you.

The next part is where it gets interesting. The screen is probably calibrated totally wrong for touch so fire up the calibration tool you installed from the file above and use this touch pen to calibrate - it will write out /etc/X11/xorg.conf.d/99-calibrate.conf with the new settings. All of this will require your keyboard.

By the way, I also installed matchbox-keyboard to allow this raspberry pi the ability to work without an attached keyboard just using the touch screen.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;sudo apt install matchbox-keyboard&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
## configure fauxmo and Alexa

Installing fauxmo and configuring it is where it gets fun because it allows you to use Alexa to fire up MagicMirror or shut it down so the raspberry pi can be used for browsing the internet or whatever you choose.

The documentation for fauxmo is good but not great. It will get you just so far but fails to provide examples of HTML code to use with it but I will remedy that situation here. The original fauxmo code build is located here: [makemuse fauxmo](https://github.com/makermusings/fauxmo.git). However, to confuse things, there is another build that is more &amp;quot;sophisticated&amp;quot; (for me it is more complicated) and is available using python pip. It also has limited documentation and configuring it can be a challenge so I am sticking with the original makermuse version of fauxmo. 

To install:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;git clone &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/makermusings/fauxmo.git&#34;&gt;https://github.com/makermusings/fauxmo.git&lt;/a&gt;
cd fauxmo
sudo cp fauxmo.py /usr/local/bin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;you-will-need-to-edit-configure-usr-local-bin-fauxmo-py&#34;&gt;you will need to edit/configure /usr/local/bin/fauxmo.py&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
You can put fauxmo.py on any server but you want to put it on one that stays up all the time.
For me that is a raspberry pi that I use as my master server (rasp1)

You can run the trigger webserver on any other server or the same on but in this case it will be the one where you have magicmirror running (rasp5).

You need to: 
 - configure the fauxmo.py script on your master server (rasp1 for my network)
 - install an rc startup script for fauxmo on your master server (rasp1 for my network)
 - write some simple html/php code to run on a webserver (with php) where magicmirror is installed
 - write a simple shell launch/kill script for magicmirror where magicmirror is installed
 - make sure your firewalls allow the needed ports 1900 52001 52002 on the master server and port 80 for the magicmirror server
 - tell Alexa to find devices
 - test Alexa and enjoy

First step: configure fauxmo.py:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FAUXMOS = [
    [&amp;lsquo;garage door&amp;rsquo;,rest_api_handler(&amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://192.168.1.63/fauxmo.php?garage_door=1&#39;,&#39;http://192.168.1.63/fauxmo.php?garage_door=0&#39;),52001&#34;&gt;http://192.168.1.63/fauxmo.php?garage_door=1&#39;,&#39;http://192.168.1.63/fauxmo.php?garage_door=0&#39;),52001&lt;/a&gt;],
    [&amp;lsquo;kitchen pie&amp;rsquo;,rest_api_handler(&amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://192.168.1.65/fauxmo.php?switch=on&#39;,&#39;http://192.168.1.65/fauxmo.php?switch=off&#39;),52002&#34;&gt;http://192.168.1.65/fauxmo.php?switch=on&#39;,&#39;http://192.168.1.65/fauxmo.php?switch=off&#39;),52002&lt;/a&gt;],
]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;This section is near line 340 or so.
Use whatevername you want ... in this case I used &amp;quot;kitchen pie&amp;quot; so my command to Alexa will be 
&amp;gt; Alexa turn on kitchen pie
or
&amp;gt; Alexa kitchen pi off
The IP address is for the server where I have a webserver and magicmirror running. The port number 52002 is my selection and can be
any unprivileged port you desire but do not leave the port optional - Alexa remembers this port number for triggering the related device name.

fauxmo.py runs as a daemon on your master server and serves up configured device names and ports when queried by Alexa on port 1900. So you need to make sure your firewall is open on port 1900 to this server thus allowing Alexa to find the devices. When the user tells Alexa to turn a named device on or off it will relay the request to the repective port... for the example above &amp;quot;kitchen pie&amp;quot; will be triggered through port 52002.

The fauxmo.py daemon will in turn send out an HTML GET request to the declared port with the configured URI -- in this case
`http://192.168.1.65/fauxmo.php?switch=on` (or off). We will get to what fauxmo.php looks like in a minute.

Now create a script to fire /usr/local/bin/fauxmo.py up on bootup:
Create /etc/init.d/fauxmorc with this content:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;begin-init-info&#34;&gt;BEGIN INIT INFO&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;provides-fauxmo&#34;&gt;Provides:          fauxmo&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;required-start&#34;&gt;Required-Start:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;required-stop&#34;&gt;Required-Stop:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;should-start&#34;&gt;Should-Start:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;default-start-2-3-4-5&#34;&gt;Default-Start:     2 3 4 5&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;default-stop&#34;&gt;Default-Stop:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;short-description-run-fauxmo-as-a-listening-server-emulates-a-wemo-hub&#34;&gt;Short-Description: Run fauxmo as a listening server - emulates a wemo hub&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;description&#34;&gt;Description:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;end-init-info&#34;&gt;END INIT INFO&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PATH=/usr/local/bin:/home/geoffm/dev/utils:/home/geoffm/bin:/usr/local/sbin:/usr/sbin:/usr/bin:/sbin:/bin:/usr/games:/usr/local/games:/snap/bin:/home/geoffm/dev/utils:/usr/share/ruby-rvm/bin:/home/geoffm/.rvm/bin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PATH=$PATH:/sbin:/usr/sbin:/bin:/usr/bin
. /lib/init/vars.sh&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PATH=$PATH:/usr/local/bin
CMD=&amp;ldquo;fauxmo.py -d&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;do_start () {
  sleep 5 # not sure if this will help # gwm 20160903
  echo &amp;ldquo;Now running: $CMD &amp;amp;&amp;rdquo; | tee -a /tmp/fauxmorc
        $CMD &amp;amp;
}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;do_status () {
        #if ps -ef|grep $CMD&amp;gt;/dev/null ; then
        if ps -ef|grep $CMD|grep -v grep ; then
                return 0
         else
                return 4
        fi
}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;case &amp;ldquo;$1&amp;rdquo; in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;start&#34;&gt;start|&amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;start)
          do_start
        ;;
  restart|reload|force-reload)
          echo &amp;ldquo;Error: argument &amp;lsquo;$1&amp;rsquo; not supported&amp;rdquo; &amp;gt;&amp;amp;2
          exit 3
        ;;
  stop)
          # No-op
   kill $( ps -ef | grep $CMD | grep -v grep | awk &amp;lsquo;{print $2}&amp;rsquo; )
    do_status
        ;;
  status)
    ps -ef | grep $CMD | grep -v grep
          do_status
          exit $?
        ;;
  *)
          echo &amp;ldquo;Usage: $0 [start|stop|status]&amp;rdquo; &amp;gt;&amp;amp;2
          exit 3
        ;;
esac&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Enable and start this script with these commands:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;sudo systemctl daemon-reload # to let systemctl know you changed things
sudo systemctl enable fauxmorc # to tell systemctl to enable this script after each reboot
sudo systemctl start fauxmorc # to fire it up&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Verify that it is running with something like `ps -ef | grep fauxmo`

Now lets go write the trigger scripts on the magicmirror server.
Set up apache2 or nginx with PHP. Write this script: /var/www/html/fauxmo.php (or call it whatever you called it in the fauxmo.py configuration.

NOTE: where you see &amp;quot;myname&amp;quot; substitute your username where MagicMirror got installed.

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;?php&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;configure-options&#34;&gt;configure options&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$get_key=&amp;ldquo;switch&amp;rdquo;;
$exec_script_on=&amp;ldquo;sudo -u myname -i /var/www/scripts/mm2ctrl.sh on&amp;rdquo;;
$exec_script_off=&amp;ldquo;sudo -u myname -i /var/www/scripts//mm2ctrl.sh off&amp;rdquo;;
$exec_script_stat=&amp;ldquo;sudo -u myname -i /var/www/scripts//mm2ctrl.sh stat&amp;rdquo;;
$exec_script_test=&amp;ldquo;sudo -u myname -i /var/www/scripts//mm2ctrl.sh test&amp;rdquo;;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;main-code&#34;&gt;Main Code&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;switch ($_GET[$get_key]) {
    case &amp;ldquo;on&amp;rdquo;:
        $full_cmd=$exec_script_on.&amp;rdquo; &amp;gt;/dev/null &amp;amp;&amp;ldquo;;
        break;
    case &amp;ldquo;off&amp;rdquo;:
        $full_cmd=$exec_script_off.&amp;rdquo; &amp;gt;/dev/null &amp;amp;&amp;ldquo;;
        break;
    case &amp;ldquo;stat&amp;rdquo;:
        $full_cmd=$exec_script_stat;
        break;
    case &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo;:
        $full_cmd=$exec_script_test;
        break;
    default:
        header(&amp;ldquo;HTTP/1.1 900 NOT OK&amp;rdquo;);
        echo &amp;ldquo;Unrecognized switch command [&amp;ldquo;.$_GET[$get_key].&amp;ldquo;] given&amp;rdquo;;
        # end exit so the command below does not try to execute
        exit;
}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;if-all-is-well-after-the-checks-execute-the-proper-command&#34;&gt;if all is well after the checks, execute the proper command&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;header(&amp;ldquo;HTTP/1.1 200 OK&amp;rdquo;);
$output=shell_exec($full_cmd);
echo &amp;ldquo;&lt;pre&gt;&amp;rdquo;.$output.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/pre&gt;&amp;rdquo;;
?&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
You notice that this script actually executes another script to accomplish running or killing off magicmirror.
That script is, in my case, /var/www/scripts/mm2ctrl.sh which looks like this:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#!/bin/bash&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;globals&#34;&gt;GLOBALS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PATH=/usr/local/sbin:/usr/local/bin:/usr/sbin:/usr/bin:/sbin:/bin
dtime=&lt;code&gt;date +%Y%m%d-%H%M&lt;/code&gt;
LOG_FILE=/tmp/mm2ctrl.sh.out
BASE_DIR=/home/myname/MagicMirror&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;functions&#34;&gt;FUNCTIONS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#########
killike ()
#########
{
  kill -9 &lt;code&gt;ps -aef | grep $1 | grep -v &amp;quot;grep &amp;quot;|awk &#39;{print $2}&#39;&lt;/code&gt;;
}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#################&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;main-code-1&#34;&gt;Main Code&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#################
echo Changing dir to $BASE_DIR
cd $BASE_DIR&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;on&#34;&gt;on&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if [ x$1 = &amp;ldquo;xon&amp;rdquo; ] ; then
  export DISPLAY=:0
  #DISPLAY=:0 nohup npm start &amp;amp;
  nohup npm start &amp;amp;
  killike xscreensaver
  xset s reset
  xset dpms force on
  echo ${dtime}: Turning on MagicMirror | tee -a $LOG_FILE
  ps -ef | grep npm  | tee -a $LOG_FILE
fi&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;off&#34;&gt;off&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if [ x$1 = &amp;ldquo;xoff&amp;rdquo; ] ; then
  killike npm
  killike electron
  echo ${dtime}: Turning off MagicMirror | tee -a $LOG_FILE
  ps -ef | grep npm |tee -a $LOG_FILE
  ps -ef | grep electron | tee -a $LOG_FILE
  nohup xscreensaver -display :0 -no-splash &amp;amp;
fi&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stat-us&#34;&gt;stat[us]&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if [ x$1 = &amp;ldquo;xstat&amp;rdquo; ] ; then
  ps -ef | grep npm
  ps -ef | grep electron
  netstat -an|grep 8080
fi&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if [ x$1 = &amp;ldquo;xtest&amp;rdquo; ]; then
  export DISPLAY=:0
  xset s reset
  xset dpms force on
  xset q
fi&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;echo Finished&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;eof&#34;&gt;EOF&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Privileges for the files is important and can be a show stopper.
Use &lt;code&gt;sudo visudo /etc/sudoers.d/www-data&lt;/code&gt; and add just this one line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;www-data ALL=(myname) NOPASSWD: ALL
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DANGER: do not let this server live out on the internet because you have to give www-data shell privileges and that is VERY INSECURE!
The line in my /etc/passwd file for www-data is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;www-data:x:33:33:www-data:/var/www:/usr/sbin/nologin
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to play with this shell script a lot and with the calling php script to get it all to work as expected. One thing to keep
in mind is that Alexa wants a fairly quick response of HTML code 200 OK or it will fail. So I worked to get the execution of underlying commands to happen in the background allowing the php script to quickly return the 200 OK html code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I added the capability to look at the status but Alex and fauxmo.py will never execute that - it is only for your use should you need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure your firewall port is open for 80 (http) on this (maginmirror) server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things should work for you now.
Try: &lt;code&gt;Alexa turn on kitchen pie&lt;/code&gt; - or whatever name you used for the &amp;ldquo;device&amp;rdquo;. When complications occur check the http access and error log on the magicmirror server and the syslog on the fauxmo.py server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;one-last-tweak-configuring-magicmirror&#34;&gt;one last tweak - configuring magicmirror&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add any modules you want to magicmirror but because the 5inch touchscreen is size challenged you will have to work to provide room for all the info you want to display. The easiest way for me to share what I did is to show you my config for magic mirror.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/MichMich/MagicMirror/wiki/MagicMirror%C2%B2-Modules&#34;&gt;MagicMirror2 modules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NOTE: the Carousel plugin was instrumental in allowing all the info to be rotated in magicmirror.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am listing the possible position settings: top_ bar, top_left, top_center, top_right, upper_third, middle_center, lower_third, bottom_left, bottom_center, bottom_right, bottom_bar, fullscreen_above, and fullscreen_below. In the MagicMirror files structure you will find a custom.css file in the css directory waiting for you to put in any overrides you want. This link will give you an idea of how the regions are setup by default &lt;a href=&#34;https://forum.magicmirror.builders/topic/286/regions&#34;&gt;MagicMirror regions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the contents of $HOME/MagicMirror/config/config.js&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/* Magic Mirror Config Sample
 *
 * By Michael Teeuw http://michaelteeuw.nl
 * MIT Licensed.
 */

var config = {
  port: 8080,
  ipWhitelist: [&amp;quot;127.0.0.1&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;192.168.1.71&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;::ffff:127.0.0.1&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;::1&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;::ffff:192.168.1.71&amp;quot;],
  language: &#39;en&#39;,
  timeFormat: 12,
  units: &#39;imperial&#39;,

  modules: [
    {
      module: &#39;MMM-Carousel&#39;,
      config: {
        ignoreModules: [ &#39;alert&#39;,&#39;stocks&#39;,&#39;MMM-RandomPhoto&#39;,&#39;clock&#39;,&#39;currentweather&#39; ],
        transitionalInterval: 35000
      }
    },
    {
      module: &#39;alert&#39;,
    Y},
    {
      module: &amp;quot;updatenotification&amp;quot;,
      position: &amp;quot;top_bar&amp;quot;
    },
    {
      module: &#39;clock&#39;,
      position: &#39;top_left&#39;
    },
    {
      module: &#39;calendar&#39;,
      header: &#39;US Holidays&#39;,
      position: &#39;top_left&#39;,
      config: {
        calendars: [
          {
            symbol: &#39;calendar-check-o &#39;,
            url: &#39;webcal://www.calendarlabs.com/templates/ical/US-Holidays.ics&#39;
          }
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      module: &#39;compliments&#39;,
      //position: &#39;lower_center&#39;
      position: &#39;top_left&#39;
    },
    {
      module: &#39;currentweather&#39;,
      position: &#39;bottom_right&#39;,
      config: {
        location: &#39;Elizabeth City&#39;,
        locationID: &#39;4465088&#39;, //ID from http://www.openweathermap.org
        appid: &#39;aee32e69be313e1f94557d6a1fc8b075&#39;
      }
    },
    {
      module: &#39;weatherforecast&#39;,
      position: &#39;top_left&#39;,
      header: &#39;Weather Forecast&#39;,
      config: {
        location: &#39;Elizabeth City&#39;,
        locationID: &#39;4465088&#39;, //ID from http://www.openweathermap.org
        appid: &#39;aee32e69be313e1f94557d6a1fc8b075&#39;
      }
    },
    {
      module: &#39;newsfeed&#39;,
      //position: &#39;bottom_bar&#39;,
      //position: &#39;top_bar&#39;,
      //position: &#39;upper_third&#39;,
      position: &#39;top_left&#39;,
      config: {
        feeds: [
          {
            title: &amp;quot;New York Times&amp;quot;,
            url: &amp;quot;http://www.nytimes.com/services/xml/rss/nyt/HomePage.xml&amp;quot;
          },
          {
            title: &amp;quot;BBC&amp;quot;,
            url: &amp;quot;http://feeds.bbci.co.uk/news/video_and_audio/news_front_page/rss.xml?edition=uk&amp;quot;,
          },
        ],
        showSourceTitle: true,
        showPublishDate: true,
        updateInterval: 20000
      }
    },
//    {
//      module: &#39;helloworld&#39;,
//      position: &#39;bottom_bar&#39;,
//      config: {
//          text: &#39;hello world!&#39;
//        }
//    },
    {
      module: &#39;MMM-RandomPhoto&#39;,
      position: &#39;fullscreen_below&#39;,
      config: {
        opacity: 0.3,
        animationSpeed: 500,
        updateInterval: 60,
        url: &#39;https://unsplash.it/1920/1080/?random&#39;
      }
    },
//    {
//      module: &#39;MMM-Remote-Control&#39;,
//      // uncomment the following line to show the URL of the remote control on the mirror
//      position: &#39;bottom_left&#39;
//      // you can hide this module afterwards from the remote control itself
//    },
    {
      module: &#39;stocks&#39;,
      position: &#39;bottom_bar&#39;,
      config: {
        stocks: &#39;.DJI,IBM,AAPL,GOOG,INTC,CSCO,ABBV,FDC,SQ,M,CVS,CVEO&#39;,
        updateInterval: 41000
      }
    },
    {
      module: &#39;random_quotes&#39;,
//      position: &#39;upper_third&#39;,
        position: &#39;top_left&#39;,
        config: {
        // The config property is optional
        // Without a config, a random quote is shown,
        // selected from all of the categories available.
          updateInterval: 120
//        category: &#39;positive&#39;
        }
    },
    {
      module: &#39;MMM-DailyBibleVerse&#39;,
      //position: &#39;top_left&#39;,
      position: &#39;upper_third&#39;,
      config: {
      version: &#39;NIV&#39; // This can be changed to any version you want that is offered by Bible Gateway. For a list, go here: https://www.biblegateway.com/usage/linking/versionslist/
      }
    },
//   {
//    module: &#39;DailyXKCD&#39;,
//    position: &#39;top_left&#39;,
//    config: {
//        invertColors: true,
//        title: true,
//        altText: false
//      }
//   },
  ]
};

/*************** DO NOT EDIT THE LINE BELOW ***************/
if (typeof module !== &#39;undefined&#39;) {module.exports = config;}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck and enjoy!
-g-&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sorting IPs</title>
      <link>/post/post-title/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 15:53:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/post-title/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I scan my home network frequently. There are a good number of smarthome devices, raspberry pies, phones,
laptops, PCs etc. Using nmap to quickly scan a network is too slow for me - and it is a challenge to
parse the output for easy reading (of course I would use awk to do that). So I use arp-scan (available
in most repositories). So output might look like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo arp-scan -I wlo1 192.168.1.0/24
Interface: wlo1, datalink type: EN10MB (Ethernet)
Starting arp-scan 1.8.1 with 256 hosts (http://www.nta-monitor.com/tools/arp-scan/)
192.168.1.1     44:94:fc:93:4f:26       (Unknown)
192.168.1.2     00:17:88:2a:b5:12       Philips Lighting BV
192.168.1.17    b8:27:eb:42:e9:01       (Unknown)
192.168.1.62    b8:27:eb:42:e9:01       (Unknown)
192.168.1.72    b8:27:eb:42:e9:01       (Unknown)


192.168.1.4     50:f5:da:52:08:8b       (Unknown)
192.168.1.90    54:42:49:a4:d7:b0       Sony Corporation
192.168.1.11    64:eb:8c:6f:e7:4c       (Unknown)
192.168.1.13    5c:ff:35:21:21:d4       Wistron Corporation
192.168.1.8     7c:c7:09:88:07:79       (Unknown)
192.168.1.17    c8:3a:35:cb:90:8f       Tenda Technology Co., Ltd. (DUP: 2)
192.168.1.10    c0:c1:c0:dc:29:69       Cisco-Linksys, LLC
192.168.1.7     6c:ad:f8:33:09:e8       (Unknown)
192.168.1.21    f0:25:b7:35:e7:33       (Unknown)
192.168.1.29    c0:c1:c0:dc:29:69       Cisco-Linksys, LLC
192.168.1.61    b8:27:eb:4b:b6:4c       (Unknown)
192.168.1.76    1c:3e:84:5e:b5:bc       (Unknown)
192.168.1.64    c0:c1:c0:dc:29:69       Cisco-Linksys, LLC
192.168.1.62    c8:3a:35:cb:90:8f       Tenda Technology Co., Ltd. (DUP: 2)
192.168.1.72    c8:3a:35:cb:90:8f       Tenda Technology Co., Ltd. (DUP: 2)
192.168.1.20    b2:c5:54:0b:de:50       (Unknown)
192.168.1.24    00:0d:4b:80:18:6d       Roku, LLC
192.168.1.131   50:c7:bf:13:44:73       (Unknown)

23 packets received by filter, 0 packets dropped by kernel
Ending arp-scan 1.8.1: 256 hosts scanned in 1.576 seconds (162.44 hosts/sec). 23 responded

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this listing is unsorted; I need it in ascending IP order. The solution is to creatively
use the unix sort command declaring the field &amp;ldquo;termination&amp;rdquo; character as &amp;ldquo;.&amp;rdquo; and then declaring
the key fields to sort on. Here is the final run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo arp-scan -I wlo1 192.168.1.0/24|sort -t . -k3,3n -k4,4n

24 packets received by filter, 0 packets dropped by kernel
Interface: wlo1, datalink type: EN10MB (Ethernet)
Starting arp-scan 1.8.1 with 256 hosts (http://www.nta-monitor.com/tools/arp-scan/)
192.168.1.1     44:94:fc:93:4f:26       (Unknown)
192.168.1.2     00:17:88:2a:b5:12       Philips Lighting BV
192.168.1.4     50:f5:da:52:08:8b       (Unknown)
192.168.1.7     6c:ad:f8:33:09:e8       (Unknown)
192.168.1.8     7c:c7:09:88:07:79       (Unknown)
192.168.1.10    c0:c1:c0:dc:29:69       Cisco-Linksys, LLC
192.168.1.11    64:eb:8c:6f:e7:4c       (Unknown)
192.168.1.13    5c:ff:35:21:21:d4       Wistron Corporation
192.168.1.17    b8:27:eb:42:e9:01       (Unknown)
192.168.1.17    c8:3a:35:cb:90:8f       Tenda Technology Co., Ltd. (DUP: 2)
192.168.1.20    b2:c5:54:0b:de:50       (Unknown)
192.168.1.21    f0:25:b7:35:e7:33       (Unknown)
192.168.1.24    00:0d:4b:80:18:6d       Roku, LLC
192.168.1.29    c0:c1:c0:dc:29:69       Cisco-Linksys, LLC
192.168.1.61    b8:27:eb:4b:b6:4c       (Unknown)
192.168.1.62    b8:27:eb:42:e9:01       (Unknown)
192.168.1.62    c8:3a:35:cb:90:8f       Tenda Technology Co., Ltd. (DUP: 2)
192.168.1.63    b2:c5:54:0b:de:50       (Unknown)
192.168.1.64    c0:c1:c0:dc:29:69       Cisco-Linksys, LLC
192.168.1.72    b8:27:eb:42:e9:01       (Unknown)
192.168.1.72    c8:3a:35:cb:90:8f       Tenda Technology Co., Ltd. (DUP: 2)
192.168.1.76    1c:3e:84:5e:b5:bc       (Unknown)
192.168.1.90    54:42:49:a4:d7:b0       Sony Corporation
192.168.1.131   50:c7:bf:13:44:73       (Unknown)
Ending arp-scan 1.8.1: 256 hosts scanned in 1.520 seconds (168.42 hosts/sec). 24 responded
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy
-g-&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick N Dirty Python Debug Function</title>
      <link>/post/quick-n-dirty-python-debug-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 14:08:05 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/quick-n-dirty-python-debug-function/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Pdb is a great debugger for python but I like to use my own simple debug functions.
Here is a simple debug function for python which could definitely be improved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;#!/usr/bin/env python

import os
import sys
from inspect import (getframeinfo, currentframe, getouterframes)


DBUG=2 # will print to stdout if set to 1 -- use 2 to add funcname and funcdocs
#DLOG=os.path.basename(sys.argv[0])+&amp;quot;.log&amp;quot; # will append to log to file if this is not commented out

def dbug(msg):
  &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
   At the top of your script set these global values:
    from inspect import (getframeinfo, currentframe, getouterframes)
    DBUG=2 # will print to stdout if set to 1 -- use 2 to add funcname and funcdocs
    #DLOG=os.path.basename(sys.argv[0])+&amp;quot;.log&amp;quot; # will append to log to file if this is not commented out
   Function: dbug() will print (or log) DEBUG: (datetime) [lineno] msg
   print this function doc with CLI help(dbug) or CODE dbug.__doc__
   needs: from inspect import currentframe.
   Simple to use... dbug(&amp;quot;my message here&amp;quot;)
   &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;

  cf = currentframe()
  msg=&amp;quot;DEBUG: [&amp;quot;+str(cf.f_back.f_lineno)+&amp;quot;] &amp;quot;+msg

  try:
    if DBUG==2:
      fname=str(getframeinfo(currentframe().f_back).function)
      fdoc=eval(fname+.__doc__
      fdoc=fdoc if fdoc else &#39;undocumented&#39;
      msg=msg+&amp;quot; Func: &amp;quot;+fname+&amp;quot; Doc: &amp;quot;+fdoc
  except:
    pass

  try:
    if DLOG != &amp;quot;&amp;quot;:
      fh_dbug=open(DLOG,&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;)
      fh_dbug.write(dtime+&amp;quot; &amp;quot;+msg+&amp;quot;\n&amp;quot;)
      fh_dbug.close
  except:
    pass

  try:
    if DBUG&amp;gt;=0:
      print msg
  except:
    pass

def myFunc(myvar=&amp;quot;eulav&amp;quot;):
  &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
   myFunc(&amp;quot;something&amp;quot;) -requires one string
   prints out the string backwards - it uses the extended slice operator
   ie [begin:end:step]
   The default here prints &amp;quot;value&amp;quot;
  &amp;quot;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
  dbug(&amp;quot;how does it work&amp;quot;)
  print myvar[::-1]

### Main Code ###
if __name__ == &#39;__main__&#39;:
  dbug(&amp;quot;Please note that the name of this function is dbug -- not debug just to avoid conflicts elsewhere&amp;quot;)

  dbug(&amp;quot;How does this work?&amp;quot;)
  myFunc(&amp;quot;this is my string&amp;quot;)

  DBUG=1
  dbug(&amp;quot;And now the reverse&amp;quot;)
  myFunc(&amp;quot;gnirts ym si siht&amp;quot;)

  dbug(&amp;quot;Let see what the default is...&amp;quot;)
  myFunc() # reverses the default
### EOF ####
&#39;&#39;&#39;

Output from this should look something like this:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DEBUG: [97] Please note that the name of this function is dbug &amp;ndash; not debug just to avoid conflicts elsewhere
DEBUG: [98] How does this work?
DEBUG: [92] how does it work Func: myFunc Doc:
   myFunc(&amp;ldquo;something&amp;rdquo;) -requires one string
   prints out the string backwards - it uses the extended slice operator
   ie [begin:end:step]
   The default here print &amp;ldquo;value&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;gnirts ym si siht
DEBUG: [102] And now the reverse
DEBUG: [92] how does it work
this is my string
DEBUG: [105] Let see what the default is&amp;hellip;
DEBUG: [92] how does it work
value
```&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!
-g-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###
Enjoy
-g-&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Raspberry Pi and Xrdp</title>
      <link>/post/raspberry-pi-and-xrdp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2016 12:27:36 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/raspberry-pi-and-xrdp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I decided to have some remote desktop fun with one of my raspberry pies. Remote desktop for the raspberry pi (or
any linux machine) can be done so many different ways - but the easiest from my perspective is xrdp. It is available
really on any linux distro and works with Windows remote desktop protocol (kinda). It requires that you install
xrdp and tightvncserver (under the covers it uses a vnc server - thightvncserver is probably the best choice here).
Then as a client on my laptop I use the very good remote desktop client called remmina; again it is availalbe on
almost any linux distro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you launch remmina it will ask for a username and password for a connection onto the IP machine you declare in the setup.
If the xrdp service is properly running on the remote machine it will server up a personal desktop for the user login
independant of any other desktop sessions that might be running.
But - I am a fan of enlightment desktop e17 for a whole lot of reasons, many of which are personal history. Enlightenment desktop
is lightweight so it works well on a raspberry pi. My task was to install e17 onto the raspberry pi and it becomes an
alternet desktop and then make it available to me over xrdp. My quick searches on the internet turned up a good deal of bogus
dead ends but I looked over the startup scripts for xsession and noticed it by default looks for and will launch&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-$HOME/.xsession```.&#34;&gt;
I am using Raspbian 8.0 debian jessie on my raspberry pi. Well, no, actually, I am using berryboot to launch Rasbian 8.0 but that
has no bearing on this discussion. Rasbian now comes with the pixel desktop which includes the lxterminal program by default
so I call that up in my ```$HOME/.xsession``` script before launching the enlightnement destop. Here is my script

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#!/usr/bin/env bash
lxterminal &amp;amp;
enlightenment_start&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
Then restart the xrdp service with:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;sudo systemctl restart xrdp.service
```&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it is your first launch of enightenment you will have to go through the brief setup - for the most part, pick the defaults and happy days are here again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh but then you will run into this rather serious problem - half of your keys won&amp;rsquo;t work! I have a solution but it probably
isn&amp;rsquo;t the best solution - it just happens to be the  only one I came across that worked for me.
Use the mouse in enlightenment and navigate through &lt;code&gt;Settings-&amp;gt;All-&amp;gt;Input-&amp;gt;Key Bindings ... click on Delete All&lt;/code&gt;
This works and you lose keybindings that you probably wouldn&amp;rsquo;t use through vnc anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy
-g-&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sometimes It Is The Obvious</title>
      <link>/post/sometimes-it-is-the-obvious/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 16:36:42 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/sometimes-it-is-the-obvious/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This was one of those &amp;ldquo;problems&amp;rdquo; that nagged me for many hours until the obvious dawned on me.
I wrote a python script to grab the temperature and humidiy from a DHT22 sensor and then write the
output with the proper syntax to send to my monitoring program [xymon]. The wrapper bash script ran
every 5 minutes and used a redirection to write out a file ie:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;*/5 * * * * /usr/local/bin/temphum.sh &amp;gt;/tmp/temphum.dat
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wrapper script grabs output and sends it to the server. Having this wrapper script lets me run the
python script independantly for testing or for curiousity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It all worked fine but sometimes the temp would jump in one direction or another for brief period and that
skewed the graphed - it was ugly so I decided to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I added code to the python script to look at the temperature that got recorded on the last run into the /tmp/temphum.dat
file and then judged if the measured temperature greater or less than the &amp;ldquo;last&amp;rdquo; temp by a amount greater than a &amp;ldquo;trigger&amp;rdquo; amount (I orignally set the trigger to be a full degree, that is 1.0). If the difference between the last and the measured temp was greater
than the &amp;ldquo;trigger&amp;rdquo; then I adjusted the measured temp up or down appropriately by and adjustment amount (0.2). This would smooth
out the graph and with the readings being taken each 5 minutes everything would work out fine over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all worked fine each time I ran it from the command line. But when the the temperature recorded into the /tmp/temphum.dat
file was always the measured temp. The adjusted temperature never made it into the file unless I ran it from the command line.
I assumed the problem was with the environment - this is a natural assumption given that when a cron job runs it inherits no
environment settings. I adapated the python script to have its own environment PATH and I also changed the bash wrapper script
to preset it&amp;rsquo;s own PATH settings. But all to no avail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I realized the problem. As soon as the wrapper script runs, it opens a redirection out to &amp;gt;/tmp/temphum.dat. That is also the
file that the python script reads but as soon as the redirection starts it &amp;ldquo;zeros out&amp;rdquo; the file - it builds an empty file. Now the
python script has no &amp;ldquo;last&amp;rdquo; temperature to read and my script rightfully drops a null last temperature reading and therefore does no adjusting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution was to drop the redirection from the cron entry and have the python script first open the /tmp/temphum.dat file for reading the last temperature, close the file, do the adjustment calculation, then re-open the file for &amp;ldquo;w&amp;rdquo;rite which empties the file for writing new content, then write the needed message lines to the file, and then close the file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All is good now. So easy to overlook the simple/obvious show stopper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy
-g-&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Always Use Visudo</title>
      <link>/post/alway-use-visudo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2016 10:59:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/alway-use-visudo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Familiarity breeds contempt&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get very comfortable with using the vim editor (take cover&amp;hellip; flame way ensuing) so
comfortable that using any other editor leaves me just a bit unnerved. I constantly use it
to update sudoers. The best way to modify sudoers is to add a supplimental inclusion file under
/etc/sudoers.d/whatevername - so the other day I needed to add an entry to allow the user for my
simple monitoring program (xymon) to be able to run &amp;ldquo;sudo ufw status&amp;rdquo; without a password and report
back to the monitor server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fired up &lt;code&gt;sudo vim /etc/sudoers.d/xymon&lt;/code&gt; and started to add the needed line:
&lt;code&gt;xymon ALL = NOPASSWD: /usr/sbin/ufw status&lt;/code&gt; but I got halfway through and could remember the exact location

of the ufw binary file.. so I saved got out and I just sawed off the limb I  was standing on. Sudo is not totally broken so I had togo to the phsical machine (which happened to be a raspberry pi) hook up a monitor and keyboard and fix it by logging in as root and finish editing the sudoers supplimental file correctly. I did it the proper way this time; I used visudo which protects you from yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesson: &lt;em&gt;Always use visudo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, to change the default editor from nano to vim for visudo (on unbuntu at least) you can run:
&lt;code&gt;sudo update-alternatives --config editor&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my systems that exchange looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo update-alternatives --config editor
There are 4 choices for the alternative editor (providing /usr/bin/editor).

  Selection    Path                Priority   Status
------------------------------------------------------------
* 0            /bin/nano            40        auto mode
  1            /bin/ed             -100       manual mode
  2            /bin/nano            40        manual mode
  3            /usr/bin/vim.basic   30        manual mode
  4            /usr/bin/vim.tiny    10        manual mode

Press &amp;lt;enter&amp;gt; to keep the current choice[*], or type selection number: 3
update-alternatives: using /usr/bin/vim.basic to provide /usr/bin/editor (editor) in manual mode
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy
-g-&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recursively Replace Text</title>
      <link>/post/recursive-replace-text/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2016 20:38:12 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/recursive-replace-text/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I had to do a find and replace text on multiple files recursively. I had to look up how to do it to remind myself of the exact syntax. If I had to look it up, you have to suffer seeing it in my blog post&amp;hellip; &lt;smile&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;find ./ -name \*.md -print0 | xargs -0 sed -i &#39;s/header-img/img/&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be careful here. I used the -0 option to deal with any filename that have spaces in the name BUT it really requires that the find command contain the -print0 option otherwise things will not operate in the manner expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy
-g-&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Switched to Hugo</title>
      <link>/post/Switched-to-Hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 10:57:45 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/Switched-to-Hugo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am swtiching from jekyll to hugo for flat file for a Content Managment System (CMS).
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/hugo-h.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;goHugo.io&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It comes as a binary file that runs on pretty much any platform. A single file&amp;hellip; without a list of dependencies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could stop with the last reason and it would be enough&amp;hellip; but I have to say that the file tree used in hugo is simple, and simple is beautiful. As Einstein once said:
&amp;gt;Make things as simple as possible, but not simpler.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is written in googles go language&amp;hellip; so it is fast and portable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is closely tied to git so it can easily be used on github and for version maintence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it builds a clean directory [./public/] for the full site deploy and this can be rsync&amp;rsquo;d to where ever you like.
or &amp;hellip; just git push it to hithub and use something like netlify.com to host from your github!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;No frustrating&lt;/em&gt; version incompatiblities (or at least very minimal) - unlike jekyll which seemed to break on me every few months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hugo is relatively mature and has a huge developer backing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;configurable and changed without challenges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lots of themes to choose from&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;as the Hugo websites states - it makes the web fun again&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did I mention that it is a single executable file?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reference:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/#intro&#34;&gt;gohugo.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy
-g-&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Converting Images</title>
      <link>/post/Converting-Images/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 11:58:20 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/Converting-Images/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have fought with trying to remember the syntax for Imagemagik&amp;rsquo;s convert command for years. I finaly caved in [from my normal position of &amp;ldquo;if you can&amp;rsquo;t do it from the commandline, then you are a wimp&amp;rdquo; and sought out a gui to help me quickly convert images to use on a website. Or to just roll a picture 90 or 180 degrees. The easy solution and a standard ubuntu repository file is &amp;ldquo;converseen&amp;rdquo;. It can do batch conversions or on selected files. Gets the job done without the challenge of looking up all the arguments for &amp;ldquo;convert&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>shell/bash uppercase arguments</title>
      <link>/post/2015-05-11-post1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-05-11-post1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To make a long story short&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/bin/bash
PATTERN=$(echo $1 | tr [:lower:] [:upper:])
# or
PATTERN=$(echo $1 | tr [a-z] [A-Z])
# or
PATTERN=$(echo $1 | awk &#39;{print toupper($0)}&#39;)

echo &amp;quot;Your \$1 argument is now uppercase: $1&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make a short story long&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to let you know a little more about me and reveal
a few more shells tricks along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am a very conservative investor - always have been but
the low interest rates over the recent past has forced me
to try a squeeze a little more out of the stock market also
known as a &amp;ldquo;a gentleman&amp;rsquo;s gambling parlor of greedy people&amp;rdquo;.
To do this I have been using covered secure puts and covered calls (did
I mention that I am conservative?). So what does this have to
do with the title here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heavily use scripting to quickly determine current positions
on stocks I track. It starts with a file listing details of
those stocks on each line. Then run a script that will selectively
get the current price on each of stock and calculate how close
it is to my target option price. I am lazy - which is one indispensable
trait of a good system admin or programmer (never do anything manually
more than once). So I needed a way to get stock quotes on
one of the stocks in my list. The obvious solution is to grab the stock
out of the list using grep (or awk) but all the stocks need to
be uppercase. I scrape the current price off of a financial site but it
requires uppercase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mention all this because my underlying motive is to encourage people
to leverage shell tools (principally grep and awk). Fact is,
financial incentives work (maybe that is a sad thing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, my script will use command line arguments to give me
a detailed single line output of selected stocks providing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;current price, difference from target and %difference from target&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;target price and recent price, IV (implied volatility), and probability of out of the money&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how many lots to offer as Puts or Calls for the selected account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;purchase price if I bought in the past&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PE and future PE, ROE, various ratings, and 52 week range&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shares owned,percent of account(s), and any notes on the stock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of this is manually maintained and, yes, it can be tedious but I have the
time. The script grabs only what I tell it through the command line (just puts or calls
or selected stocks or all of them etc). Then it grabs the current price and tells me
how close it is to my target price as a percentage. For example I can tell the
script to just grab potential puts that are within X% (eg 6%) of its strike or target price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gives me a good starting point for doing further research on selected stocks
for the day. For example this will give me all put options that interest me where
the current price is within 6% of my target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# get stocks with interesting put options, mark anything with 6% of the target/strike price
# and grep out those marked stocks only
getquotes.sh -p -m 6 -g
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t bore you with anymore detail - besides anything after this gets pretty cryptic&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-g-&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The GrovePi kit</title>
      <link>/post/grovepi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/grovepi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;check-out-grovepi&#34;&gt;Check out GrovePi&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These kits make working with the Raspberry Pi GPIO pins
so simple and clean.  I just ordered one of these kits and
I will try to write up a review after I work it over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in building a quick and easy raspberry pi
for experimenting with the &amp;ldquo;Internet of Things&amp;rdquo; (aka IoT) platform - this board and kit
looks like it will get you there in minutes. Approx: $89 -
includes board, and &lt;em&gt;lots&lt;/em&gt; of sensors/accessories with wires
and connectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/grovepi1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;grovepi&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This company is doing cool things to make raspberry pi projects
fun and easy - especially for students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just had to share - here is their link: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dexterindustries.com/&#34;&gt;Dexter Industries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-g-&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to print the remainder of a line using awk</title>
      <link>/post/2015-05-02-post1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-05-02-post1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;#How to print remainder of line using awk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;eliminate-the-first-x-columns&#34;&gt;eliminate the first X columns&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is your challenge you have a list of cronjobs and you
want to just execute the scheduled backup command with its
arguments for a test run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using one command line, how would you do it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a sample root cronjob and I want to run the
first entry with its arguments as a test run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# m h  dom mon dow   command
 0 16  *   *   * /data/share/home/geoffm/dev/utils/bak-it.sh -i /usr/local/etc/include.lst -e /usr/local/etc/exclude.lst -t /data/bak/`hostname` -s 7 &amp;gt;/dev/null 2&amp;gt;&amp;amp;1
  5 0  *   *   * /data/share/motion/arch-files.sh &amp;gt;/dev/null 2&amp;gt;&amp;amp;1
*/15 *  *   *   * /data/share/home/geoffm/grab-pic.sh &amp;gt;/dev/null 2&amp;gt;&amp;amp;1
####### below are WIP or OLD ########
# 16 6  *   *   * /usr/sbin/lynis -c --auditor &amp;quot;automated&amp;quot; --cronjob --quiet &amp;gt;/dev/null 2&amp;gt;&amp;amp;1
#*/5 *  *   *   * /usr/local/bin/watch-proc.sh -f /usr/local/etc/watch-proc.conf -n geoffm@localhost &amp;gt;/dev/null 2&amp;gt;&amp;amp;1
#*/5 * * * * /data/share/home/geoffm/ping-pong.sh &amp;quot;ping -c2 192.168.1.55&amp;quot; &amp;quot;ssh 192.168.1.1 reboot&amp;quot; &amp;gt;/dev/null
#  7 * * * /usr/local/sbin/postfix_report.sh &amp;amp;&amp;gt; /dev/null
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how I would do it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo $(sudo crontab -l | awk &#39;/bak-it/{$1=$2=$3=$4=$5=&amp;quot;&amp;quot;;print $0}&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examining this we first see this &lt;code&gt;$(...)&lt;/code&gt; structure which tells
the shell to run whatever exists between the parens and replace the
output right there. So first we call sudo crontab -l in order to
make sure we get root&amp;rsquo;s crontab listed. The output is piped into
awk where we give it a regex to search for in each string (ie /bak-it/).
The trick here is we tell awk to make the first variable in the string
equal to the second&amp;hellip; equal to the 3rd, 4th and 5th, and finally = &amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo;.
This effectively substitutes and empty string for the first 5 variables
leaving the remained of the line which then gets printed with the
&lt;code&gt;print $0&lt;/code&gt;. Actually you can leave off the &lt;code&gt;$0&lt;/code&gt; because awk will default
to that if you just use &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now there may be one more problem. If you run that command above it
will execute the intended command along with the arguments BUT it will
do it as the user who ran it. Obviously, if the commands come from the
root crontab it may not run properly for another user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will leave it as an exercise for the reader to solve that problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating that special character in vim</title>
      <link>/post/2015-04-30-post1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-04-30-post1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;entering-special-characters-into-vim&#34;&gt;Entering special characters into vim&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use vim as my editor. Despite this first sentence, this is not a
beginning volley to an editor flame war. I will save that for another
day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever editor has its own unique features and vim definitely no stranger to
that group. One feature I use quite a bit is what vim calls digraphs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are thousands of characters other than the standard keyboard character
that can be displayed with vim. You may already know that you can use
&lt;code&gt;CTRL-v &amp;lt;enter&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to force a linefeed into even a DOS filetype. Actually
`CTRL-v &lt;ascii###&gt; will force special characters from a long list of choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I prefer using CTRL-K followed by two semi-meaningful (slightly resembles the
intended special character) to create any one of literally thousands of special
characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are in vim and you are not in INSERT mode (hit ESC a couple of times to
make sure) you can type &lt;code&gt;:digraphs&lt;/code&gt; and see the first page of possible choices.
This list is extensive and daunting when first viewed. It is really sets of 3 columns.
The first column is the digraph CTRL-k combo to create what is seen in the second
column. And the 3rd column is the &lt;code&gt;CTRL-v ###&lt;/code&gt; number to be used to create that same
character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look at an example - the first column 11 rows down you should see the way to create
the one cent character:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Ct  196 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this tells you is that if you are in the INSERT mode (Esc Esc i)
Then you can type either of these two commands to create a one cent symbol&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;CTRL-k Ct
# or
CTRV-v 196
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your scroll down the &lt;code&gt;:digraph&lt;/code&gt; list you will find just about any special
character you can imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BTW - to see what values correspond to a char - cursor to it and hit :as[cii]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are a few examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;CTRL-k 34 = 
CTRL-k 12 = 
CTRL-k -&amp;lt; = 
CTRL-k -&amp;gt; = 
CTRL-k -v = 
CTRL-k -! = 
CTRL-k &amp;lt;&amp;gt; = 
CTRL-k =&amp;gt; = 
CTRL-k OK = 
CTRL-k -X = 
CTRL-k XX = 
CTRL-k &amp;lt;&#39; = 
CTRL-k &amp;gt;&#39; = 
CTRL-k Fm = 
CTRL-k Ml = 
CTRL-k *1 =  
CTRL-k *2 = 
CTRL-k D* = 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Enjoy
&lt;br&gt;
-g-&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>git inside, git better, git stronger</title>
      <link>/post/2015-04-28-post1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-04-28-post1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;exploring-git-from-the-inside-out&#34;&gt;&amp;hellip; exploring git from the inside out &amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Preface&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p class=highcap&gt;Apologies up front - this is long&amp;hellip; very long, but there is food for the brain here.
I will discuss git for personal use. Using it with many other contributors is
an extension of the principle covered here. For simplicity, I am only going
to discuss you working alone and only using a single &amp;ldquo;branch&amp;rdquo; of code for
each project - again, for simplicity. Additionally we are going to examine
the git &amp;ldquo;database&amp;rdquo; (stored as compressed SHA-1 named files/objects) as we go.
We can gain a better understanding by reviewing the changes to the guts of
your personal git repository. We will not cover branches, tags, or the git daemon
in this discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Why git? (skip this if you are less than patient)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many years ago I used backups of my projects or just documents, notes, etc.
All worked well until it didn&amp;rsquo;t. If you make a mistake and back it up guess what,

now you have two broken copies. Then I used cvs - awesome. It worked for me
for years. Never lost code (as long as I put it under cvs). Really, maintained my
work and previous versions with only very minor issues but kept my data useful and
available. I tried git but wow, so many moving parts, and I had trouble wrapping my
head around the differences to older version control systems where a &amp;ldquo;master&amp;rdquo; copy
was kept in one place and all other copies were &amp;ldquo;clients&amp;rdquo; who shared and merged with
the master copy. But git is different and much better - every copy is a master,
fully self standing, with it&amp;rsquo;s own repository residing within the project directory
itself. Hidden in the .git directory but always working with you as your progress. Full
blown copies can be &amp;ldquo;cloned&amp;rdquo; to any other server you desire. And any set of copies
can all be merged together easily. As wonderful as this all is&amp;hellip;. alas, git has
miles and miles of depth. That, like most really powerful programs, is a good bad thing.
You can get lost in the features and they can trip you up but the secret is to learn
incrementally. Bite off small bits at a time. Take your time and the investment will
definitely be rewarding. When you extend git into a world with multiple (even many
multiples) of contributors git really shines. All your files are stored in the
.git/objects/pack/ directory with weird long name and as &lt;em&gt;read only&lt;/em&gt; protecting
you from accidental deletion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Getting Started with git&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have, over the years, always had a &amp;ldquo;$HOME/dev/&amp;rdquo; directory where I keep all my code
or even document files, graphics, etc. Really anything I want to preserve, especially
if versions are involved. So this discussion will be using $HOME/dev to place our
projects; each project with its own directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;EXERCISE&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;mkdir -p $HOME/dev/mypjct
cd $HOME/dev/myprjct
ls -ltra
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing exists in this directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can initialize (start) a git repository any time you desire.
Because you want to be very careful, you are going to initialize
your project before creating any files. This will also allow us
to see the changes to the git database (really the .git directory)
as we work with git.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git init
ls -ltra
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what your project directory looks like now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;+-----.git
|     +-----branches
|     +-----config
|     +-----description
|     +-----HEAD
|     +-----hooks
|     |     +-----applypatch-msg.sample
|     |     +-----commit-msg.sample
|     |     +-----post-update.sample
|     |     +-----pre-applypatch.sample
|     |     +-----pre-commit.sample
|     |     +-----prepare-commit-msg.sample
|     |     +-----pre-push.sample
|     |     +-----pre-rebase.sample
|     |     +-----update.sample
|     +-----info
|     |     +-----exclude
|     +-----objects
|     |     +-----info
|     |     +-----pack
|     +-----refs
|     |     +-----heads
|     |     +-----tags
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note the objects directory becuase that is where all your files changes will get recorded
as you work with git.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are going to create a test file called t.f and add the text &amp;ldquo;ver 1&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;echo &amp;quot;ver 1&amp;quot; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; t.f
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No changes have occurred to git at this point. You now have one &amp;ldquo;working&amp;rdquo; file
in your project directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now &amp;ldquo;stage&amp;rdquo; the new file [t.f] into git with this command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git add -a * # or we can use a shortcut command: git add -A (which we use going forward)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now lets look at your project directory again and note the changes from above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;+-----.git
|     +-----branches
|     +-----config
|     +-----description
|     +-----HEAD
|     +-----hooks
|     |     +-----applypatch-msg.sample
|     |     +-----commit-msg.sample
|     |     +-----post-update.sample
|     |     +-----pre-applypatch.sample
|     |     +-----pre-commit.sample
|     |     +-----prepare-commit-msg.sample
|     |     +-----pre-push.sample
|     |     +-----pre-rebase.sample
|     |     +-----update.sample
|     +-----index
|     +-----info
|     |     +-----exclude
|     +-----objects
|     |     +-----5b
|     |     |     +-----d657f7b8fcd822d6e44202bc33e808cdd01ee7
|     |     +-----info
|     |     +-----pack
|     +-----refs
|     |     +-----heads
|     |     +-----tags
+-----t.f
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we can see our new file listed last [t.f] and also a new
directory [5b] under .git/objects and a file under that
[d657f7b8fcd822d6e44202bc33e808cdd01ee7]. Here is where it gets a
little complicated just stick with me. This is one git &amp;ldquo;object&amp;rdquo; which
was a single file called [5bd657f7b8fcd822d6e44202bc33e808cdd01ee7] -
the first two characters of this file where used to create a subdirectory and
the rest of the name was used for a file name. The full name here is actually
the SHA-1 hash value of the contents of the file. Also know that the contents
of the file have been compressed with the zlib library. There is a git
command to allow you to see the contents which will do here. Just understand
that the git &amp;ldquo;object name&amp;rdquo; is really the subdirectory+filename hence
[5bd657f7b8fcd822d6e44202bc33e808cdd01ee7] and the git way to print the
contents out is a bit strange. You do not need to remember this command; it is
just so we can monitor things as we go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git cat-file -p 5bd657f7b8fcd822d6e44202bc33e808cdd01ee7
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shows the content of the file only [ver 1].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now just so you can see what can be done at this point let&amp;rsquo;s delete
your working file and then list the directory to see that it is gone
then use git to restore it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;rm t.f
ls -ltra
# your t.f file is gone!
git checkout t.f
ls -ltra
# your t.f file is back!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you examine the .git directory tree at this point you will that there are
no changes. Now lets &amp;ldquo;commit&amp;rdquo; what we &amp;ldquo;staged&amp;rdquo; earlier and then examine the
.git directory tree again to see what has occurred (we will only list
the .git/objects tree for brevity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git commit -m &amp;quot;commit of ver 1&amp;quot; # -m just means add this message - without it 
                                # you would be forced into an editor and required
                                # to add a message - a good/required habbit to get into.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the .git/objects tree:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;objects
+-----03
|     +-----f1148542c5dbf6347c7e8e6a62863258c1c3b0
+-----5b
|     +-----d657f7b8fcd822d6e44202bc33e808cdd01ee7
+-----f0
|     +-----fa0104ec53e1614f556472b6ec9e355e297d7f
+-----info
+-----pack
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our original object which was &amp;ldquo;staged&amp;rdquo; is still here under [5b] and two
new ones appear. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at the contents of each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git cat-file -p 03f1148542c5dbf6347c7e8e6a62863258c1c3b0
tree f0fa0104ec53e1614f556472b6ec9e355e297d7f
author Geoff McNamara &amp;lt;geoff.mcnamara@gmail.com&amp;gt; 1430154082 -0400
committer Geoff McNamara &amp;lt;geoff.mcnamara@gmail.com&amp;gt; 1430154082 -0400

commit ver 1

$ git cat-file -p 5bd657f7b8fcd822d6e44202bc33e808cdd01ee7
ver 1

$ git cat-file -p f0fa0104ec53e1614f556472b6ec9e355e297d7f
100644 blob 5bd657f7b8fcd822d6e44202bc33e808cdd01ee7    t.f

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s also look at the git log&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git log
commit 03f1148542c5dbf6347c7e8e6a62863258c1c3b0
Author: Geoff McNamara &amp;lt;geoff.mcnamara@gmail.com&amp;gt;
Date:   Mon Apr 27 13:01:22 2015 -0400

    commit ver 1

$ git status
On branch master
nothing to commit, working directory clean

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The git log refers to the object which has the contents of the first file we examined above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how are these files/objects/versions connected? They are chained as parent/child.
Lets examine a later (more recent) object and note it has a parent which is the object
above. First we will modify the t.f file, git add it, and commit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ echo &amp;quot;updating to ver 2&amp;quot; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; t.g
$ git add -A
$ git commit -m &amp;quot;committing ver 2&amp;quot;
$ git cat-file -p 46769acc026e57212ca06ad8991643061ac429eb
tree c828f096c4a01ca3cffa690c484b5ef8ee714a2c
parent 03f1148542c5dbf6347c7e8e6a62863258c1c3b0
author Geoff McNamara &amp;lt;geoff.mcnamara@gmail.com&amp;gt; 1430157487 -0400
committer Geoff McNamara &amp;lt;geoff.mcnamara@gmail.com&amp;gt; 1430157487 -0400

updating to ver 2

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is enough for you to start to appreciate how git stores data. Obviously
we only scratched the surface here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repositories for git exists as either a working repository or a &amp;ldquo;shared&amp;rdquo;
repository - created as &amp;ldquo;bare&amp;rdquo; with &amp;ldquo;git init &amp;ndash;bare&amp;rdquo; - more on this later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we move on please take a look at your .git/config file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cat .git/config
[core]
        repositoryformatversion = 0
        filemode = true
        bare = false
        logallrefupdates = true
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note the &amp;ldquo;bare = false&amp;rdquo; so by default this is not a &amp;ldquo;shared&amp;rdquo;
repository. It is a &amp;ldquo;working&amp;rdquo; project directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;setting-up-a-remote-shared-git-server&#34;&gt;Setting up a remote &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt;shared&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/em&gt; git server&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;#############################################&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A remote shared server can be used as a personal storage/backup of your
important code and files. It becomes especially useful if it is
universally available from anywhere by ssh or http (read: internet accessible).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;shared&lt;/em&gt; git repo is just a bit different from your self-standing git project
&amp;ldquo;working&amp;rdquo; directory. It will only contain the git structure found in your .git directory
and by convention it will have an extension on the name of [.git].
Your project .git directory has these subdirectories or files branches, config,
description, HEAD, hooks, info, objects, and refs. Your local project directory
also has your working files. A remote shared directory has no working file - it
acts only as a git repository so it has all the git files or subdirectories
but no working files. It is created differently [&lt;code&gt;git init --bare&lt;/code&gt;] and used
only remotely for checking files in (pushes) and checking them out (pulls).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a git user and a .ssh directory for that user on the remote server.
&lt;em&gt;Or&lt;/em&gt; you can use any user on the remote server&amp;hellip; just understand the permission
for the files are influenced by the user who tries to access them. We suggest
a generic user name like &amp;ldquo;git&amp;rdquo; because this repository will be shared - it will
not be a &amp;ldquo;working&amp;rdquo; project directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; sudo adduser git
 su git
 cd
 mkdir .ssh &amp;amp;&amp;amp; chmod 700 .ssh 
 touch .ssh/authorized_keys &amp;amp;&amp;amp; chmod 600 .ssh/authorized_keys
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-make-logins-easier-passwordless&#34;&gt;To make logins easier (passwordless)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to add your SSH public keys to the remote authorized_keys
file for the git user.
You should take a look at it just to be familar with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cat myhome/.ssh/id_rsa.pub
ssh-rsa AAAAB3NADAQABAAABAQCB007n/ww+ouN4gSLKssMxXnBOvf9LGt4L...dAv8JggJICUvax2T9va5... user@host
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that the content of this file is all one line.
Now append that into to the git users authorized_keys &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh-copy-id git@remote_server  # we use the tool provided by ssh 
# This will do the same as this below
# except it offers the advantage of making sure 
# the ~/.ssh directory exists on the remote server.
# 
cat /tmp/id_rsa.pub &amp;gt;&amp;gt; git@remote_server:.ssh/authorized_keys
# the above command requires that the 
# remote user .ssh directory already exists. 
# Best to use ssh-copy-id provided for this purpose
# but know you know what it is doing for you.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lock-down-the-git-user-shell&#34;&gt;Lock down the git user shell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change the git user shell to: &lt;code&gt;/usr/bin/git-shell&lt;/code&gt; on the remote server.
Make sure that git-shell exists in the &lt;code&gt;/etc/shells&lt;/code&gt; file
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;Note: you will not be able to ssh into the server as the
git user&amp;hellip; but it will allow git commands to work against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;build-an-empty-git-initialized-prepared-directory-for-every-project&#34;&gt;Build an empty git initialized/prepared directory for every project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the remote server you need to build out a project.git directory
and initialize if with &lt;code&gt;git init --bare&lt;/code&gt; to allow a new project
to be pushed to the remote server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTE: &lt;code&gt;git init --bare&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;em&gt;VERY DIFFERENT&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;code&gt;git init bare&lt;/code&gt;.
The first creates a shared git repository (with no working files).
The second command creates a local project directory named &amp;ldquo;bare&amp;rdquo;
complete with its own .git directory. The &amp;ldquo;bare&amp;rdquo; project directory
is ready to receive and git manage any new working files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create an empty shared git directory (remote repository) on the remote
server for the project (same process for any new shared project).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; cd /opt/gitroot # I used /data/gitroot - you can name this 
                 # git repo dir anything you want
 mkdir project.git # yes, add the git extension - trust me here - it is convention
 cd project.git # IMPORTANT - by convention shared git repos are named with a [.git] extension!!!
 git init --bare # build out a default git directories with needed files (it will
                 # not create .git - instead all the directories are not hidden
                 # and at the project directory level. Do an `ls -l` to see the
                 # difference
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;git init --bare&lt;/code&gt; builds out the bare .git/ directory with all the
needed structure and files for controlling git but no .git subdirectory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will look like this before any pushes are done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;+-----branches
+-----config
+-----description
+-----HEAD
+-----hooks
|     +-----applypatch-msg.sample
|     +-----commit-msg.sample
|     +-----post-update.sample
|     +-----pre-applypatch.sample
|     +-----pre-commit.sample
|     +-----prepare-commit-msg.sample
|     +-----pre-push.sample
|     +-----pre-rebase.sample
|     +-----update.sample
+-----info
|     +-----exclude
+-----objects
|     +-----info
|     +-----pack
+-----refs
|     +-----heads
|     +-----tags
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: no objects yet and no .git subdirectory (and no working files
will be stored here).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;prepare-your-project-directory-on-the-local-computer-if-you-haven-t-already&#34;&gt;Prepare your project directory on the local computer if you haven&amp;rsquo;t already&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; cd myproject # even when files already exist
 git init # to build out the .git/ directory structure and files
 git add . # stages files in the cache (staging area)
 git commit -m &#39;Initial base commit&#39; # commits the staged files to you local git repo 
 # the .git/ directory and files now has all the history and needed info making up
 # your local git repo.
 # this next command adds/changes a line in the local myproject/.git/config
 git remote add origin git@gitserver:/opt/git/project.git
 # the above line tells git you want a remote server which you are naming &amp;quot;origin&amp;quot;
 # to act as another copy of your local git repo and its location is then declared
 # This information is now stored in your prj/.git/config file - go look at it to see.
 git push origin master # this pushes your git repo up to the declared remote server
                        # which has the alias name &amp;quot;origin&amp;quot;
 # git status # note the output on this will say you are &amp;quot;on branch master&amp;quot;
 # that is the default working area.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the remote &lt;em&gt;shared&lt;/em&gt; prj.git repository might look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;+-----branches
+-----config
+-----description
+-----HEAD
+-----hooks
|     +-----applypatch-msg.sample
|     +-----commit-msg.sample
|     +-----post-update.sample
|     +-----pre-applypatch.sample
|     +-----pre-commit.sample
|     +-----prepare-commit-msg.sample
|     +-----pre-push.sample
|     +-----pre-rebase.sample
|     +-----update.sample
+-----info
|     +-----exclude
+-----objects
|     +-----03
|     |     +-----f1148542c5dbf6347c7e8e6a62863258c1c3b0
|     +-----46
|     |     +-----769acc026e57212ca06ad8991643061ac429eb
|     +-----4e
|     |     +-----f21067659fb999c8efcdb03e800245dbd80eb0
|     +-----5b
|     |     +-----d657f7b8fcd822d6e44202bc33e808cdd01ee7
|     +-----84
|     |     +-----bce25cbc083f803b75fc34f4b4577ea95c6a0b
|     +-----8a
|     |     +-----611c4dabd6b8d8654d554a8d5378656682c4f9
|     +-----c8
|     |     +-----28f096c4a01ca3cffa690c484b5ef8ee714a2c
|     +-----f0
|     |     +-----fa0104ec53e1614f556472b6ec9e355e297d7f
|     +-----f2
|     |     +-----79361d9a6ab19614d57d96cafd47a17280b02e
|     +-----info
|     +-----pack
+-----refs
|     +-----heads
|     |     +-----master
|     +-----tags
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note the additional objects and NO WORKING FILES.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, lets have just a small aside on how git is different
from other older version control programs like CVS. git likes
living all alone by itself &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; it is also just as happy to share
life with others. When you do a &lt;code&gt;git init&lt;/code&gt; it builds out a whole
new .git/ directory where - this becomes your local repository -
complete in every way - all local to your project directory.
When you do  a &lt;code&gt;git add .&lt;/code&gt; you
&amp;ldquo;stage&amp;rdquo; files. This gives you a chance to unstage file(s)
before committing them to the repository storage. Once you run &lt;code&gt;git commit&lt;/code&gt;
all the staged files are stored as copies into the local repository
and they are now available for checkout as the latest version.
Everything is self contained in your local project directory - your
original files and all changes, history, latest version etc all in
the .git/ repository. So this doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem like it offers and safety
advantages until your realize that you can &lt;em&gt;very easily&lt;/em&gt; clone everything
onto any other PC &amp;hellip; and another and another - all existing as a full
self-sufficient repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone can now clone it and push changes back up just as easily:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# from another remote machine
 git clone git@remoteserver:/opt/gitroot/project.git # clone the whole
                                                     #  enchilada - notice
                                                     # the .git extension
                                                     # denoting this is
                                                     # a shared git repos
 cd project
 vim README # make any change you want
 git commit -am &#39;Small modification to README&#39; # commits it locally
 git push origin master # pushes it to the server it was claned from above
 # go look at .git/config to gain a little better understanding
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you have it - one fully functional personal repository and one shared
repository..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-g-&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LaTex and markdown</title>
      <link>/post/2015-04-04-post1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-04-04-post1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To get \(LaTex\) to work I had to add this to the _layout/footer.html&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;script type=&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot;
    src=&amp;quot;http://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and change the _config to use redcarpet for markdown&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BTW - to get \(Latex\) in the same line use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;insert \\(LaTex\\) here
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this code&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$$a^2 + b_i^2 = c^2 \left(\frac12\right) $$
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;looks like this:
$$a^2 + b_i^2 = c^2 \left(\frac12\right)$$
or block \(Latex\):
\[ \frac{1}{n^{2}} \]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>