<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Musings on companionway</title>
    <link>https://www.companionway.net/musing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Musings on companionway</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved - companionway - 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 May 2019 08:25:04 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.companionway.net/musing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Trust Game</title>
      <link>https://www.companionway.net/musing/socialgametheory/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2019 08:25:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.companionway.net/musing/socialgametheory/</guid>
      <description>This is a very interesting game dealing with social trust, benfits of cooperation, damge of miscommunication, cheating etc.
This helps us to understand why in the middle of WWI soldiers from both side stopped fighting on Christmas day&amp;hellip;
Try this game. If you are like me, you will get sucked in just to find out what the final conclusions are&amp;hellip; only takes a few minutes of your valuable time:
https://ncase.me/trust</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HarvardX</title>
      <link>https://www.companionway.net/musing/20190423/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 20:13:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.companionway.net/musing/20190423/</guid>
      <description>HarvardX - free classes (if you audit them)
These are awesome online classes. The first one that caught me was CS50 which is a tremendous in depth overview of Computer Science &amp;mdash; really a very impressive class even if you are an old salt.
Today I got an email about a new series of classes they are offering. The Shakespeare classes have pulled me in but I would love to take them all.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Happend? The End of the Bronze Age</title>
      <link>https://www.companionway.net/musing/20190422-1036/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 10:38:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.companionway.net/musing/20190422-1036/</guid>
      <description>I frequently read history books or articles related to the origins of Western Civilization, primary Ancient Greece. You can&amp;rsquo;t read about Ancient Greece without understanding the entire Mediterranean. Recently, my fascination has focused on the collapse of the Bronze Age1, also known as the Greek Dark Ages. This reference (Greek Dark Age) is understating the situation dramatically as the destruction, poverty, and defensive conditions were pervasive across the entire Mediterranean.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mural Joe</title>
      <link>https://www.companionway.net/musing/20190420-1139/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2019 11:39:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.companionway.net/musing/20190420-1139/</guid>
      <description>Artists who can paint bring light into my world. I have watched the &amp;ldquo;Mural Joe&amp;rdquo; series on YouTube for a few years now. I came across another one today and it reminded me of how good he is at explaining colors, light, and perspective. He does murals (or at least that is how his series started) but his principalsare transferable to anything style of paining. One of the first videos I watched depicted his work on a childrens room in a hospital with a pirate scene.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amor Fati</title>
      <link>https://www.companionway.net/musing/20190419-1946/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2019 20:09:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.companionway.net/musing/20190419-1946/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The stoics of ancient Greece had an impact on many aspects of our lives. It influenced everything for Christian thought to contemporary self-help books. Today&amp;rsquo;s stoic thought revolves around &amp;ldquo;Amor Fati&amp;rdquo;, loosely defined as loving fate. This single philosophic perspective, practiced well, can change your heart and your life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2019-04-09</title>
      <link>https://www.companionway.net/musing/20190409/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2019 15:21:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.companionway.net/musing/20190409/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;musings-amid-chaos&#34;&gt;Musings amid Chaos&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;stoicism&#34;&gt;Stoicism:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being good, associating with good, and rationally accepting what is, reduces risk of peril and sets the stage for contentment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;christian&#34;&gt;Christian:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Life is a series of structured chance encounters, each designed to speak to you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nother</title>
      <link>https://www.companionway.net/musing/nother/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 14:57:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.companionway.net/musing/nother/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;just-nother-post&#34;&gt;Just &amp;lsquo;nother post&lt;/h4&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>